Finding Aid for Bennie Gaylord Oosterbaan papers, 1902-1981
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Bennie Gaylord Oosterbaan papers 1902-1981
Oosterbaan, Bennie Gaylord, 1906-
861126 Aa 2; AC; UAm
Athlete and football coach at the University of Michigan. Correspondence, scrapbooks, photographs, and other materials relating to University athletics, especially football.
1.5 linear feet
3 oversize volumes
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Bennie G. Oosterbaan (donor no. 6791 )
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Bennie G. Oosterbaan was born in Muskegon, Mich., in 1906. He graduated from the University of Michigan where he was a three-sport varsity star: in football, basketball and baseball. As an end on the football team, Oosterbaan led the Big Ten in touchdowns in 1925 with eight and was a three-time all-American and was named to an all-time all-American team. He was an all-American in basketball in 1927 and 1928.
Oosterbaan became an assistant football coach in 1928 and head coach in 1948, when Michigan went 9-0 and was ranked No. 1. During his 11 years as coach, Michigan won three Big Ten championships and achieved a Rose Bowl victory in 1951 over California, 14-6. His teams compiled a 66-33-4 record. Oosterbaan was also head basketball coach, 1938-1946, leading Michigan to an overall record of 81-72.
In 1959, Oosterbaan became Michigan's director of athletic alumni relations and held that position until he retired in 1972. He died October 25, 1990.
The Bennie G. Oosterbaan collection documents his career as athlete and coach at the University of Michigan, especially his time as head football coach. The collection is comprised of the following series: Correspondence; Papers collected from different period of his career; Miscellaneous; Scrapbooks; and Photographs. The collection relates to his career at the University of Michigan, especially as football coach.
Subjects:
Football--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Sports.; University of Michigan--Football.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Alpha Chi Omega. Theta Chapter (University of Michigan); Alpha Sigma Phi Fraternity. Theta Chapter (University of Michigan); Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Streets.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Theaters.; Arcade Theater (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Celebrations.; Christmas.; Clothing and dress--1971-1980.; Dining rooms--1921-1930.; Eating and drinking.; Football.; Harbor Springs (Mich.); Interiors.; Middle Village (Mich.); Muskegon High School (Muskegon, Mich.); North University Avenue (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Oosterbaan, Delmas.; Oosterbaan, Bennie Gaylord, 1906-; Parlors.; Rose Bowl (Football game); Streets--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Theaters--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Basketball.; University of Michigan--Football.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1921-1930.; University of Michigan--Student housing--1921-1930.; Yost, Eunice Josephine Fite, 1881-1975.; Yost, Fielding Harris, 1871-1946.
Contributors:
Hall, E. K. (Edward Kimball), 1870-1932.
Genre Terms:
Drawings.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Correspondence
  - 1928-1947 (Box 1)
  - 1948-1949 (Box 1)
  - 1950-1957 (Box 1)
  - 1958-1959 (Box 1)
  - 1969-1981 (Box 1)
  - April 1959 regarding testimonial dinner (Box 1)
  - 1958 concerning Sportsman of the Year Award (Box 1)
  - Delmas Oosterbaan correspondence 1919-1937 (Box 1)
  - Photocopies of material from a private collection (Box 1)
- Papers collected from different period of his career
  - Player at Michigan 1925-1928 (Box 1)
  - School Assembly Association 1929-1930 (Box 1)
  - Assistant Coach at Michigan 1928-1947 (Box 1)
  - Head Coach at Michigan 1948-1958 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous
  - Michigamua materia1 1927 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Michigan publications and articles (Box 1)
  - Periodicals (American Boy and Colliers with articles on BGO and Michigan football) (Folder UAm)
  - Letter and speech of E. K. Hall 1925 (Box 1)
  - Letters from servicemen 1943-1944 (Box 1)
- Scrapbooks
  (clippings, photos, and memorabilia)
  - 1926-1928 (Volume 1)
  - 1948 (cover title "The Bennie Oosterbaan story") (Volume 2)
  - 1920s scrapbook of Delmas Oosterbaan (Volume 3)
    (include photos of Alpha Chi Omega sorority, Harbor Springs, and Middle Village, Michigan)
  - 1920-1924 concerning Muskegon High and University of Michigan activities (Volume 1)
- Photographs
  - Alpha Sigma Phi, Ann Arbor, Mich. circa 1926-1927 (Box 2)
  - Awards and honors (Box 2)
  - Early photos (Box 2)
  - Football games and practice (Box 2)
  - Football players (Box 2)
    (see also oversize folder UAm)
  - Friends and colleagues (Box 2)
  - Groups (Box 2)
    (includes photo of Sphinx initiation, 1926)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Muskegon High School, 1920 football team and reunions (Box 2)
  - Portraits and snapshots (Box 2)
  - Reunions, 2 envelopes (Box 2)
  - Rose Bowl; includes photo of 1902 team (Box 2)
  - Teams; including basketball teams (Box 2)
  - Testimonial dinner, Detroit 1959 (Box 2)
  - Yost, Fielding H. and Eunice P. (Box 2)